<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of faith; wherein is laid down the ground of true faith, which sanctifieth and purifieth the heart, and worketh out the carnal part. Shewing the way that leadeth to salvation: with the difference betwixt the two seeds, the one of Mount Sinai, which tendeth to bondage; and the other, which is the immortal seed of God, begotten by the immortal word, which liveth and abideth for ever. Being as Isaac was, the childe of the promise, and of Jerusalem which is from above ... The difference betwixt the living word and the letter.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74895</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E703_6**</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50796659</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50796659</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166595</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74895)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E703[6**])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of faith; wherein is laid down the ground of true faith, which sanctifieth and purifieth the heart, and worketh out the carnal part. Shewing the way that leadeth to salvation: with the difference betwixt the two seeds, the one of Mount Sinai, which tendeth to bondage; and the other, which is the immortal seed of God, begotten by the immortal word, which liveth and abideth for ever. Being as Isaac was, the childe of the promise, and of Jerusalem which is from above ... The difference betwixt the living word and the letter.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black Spread Eagle at the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 4 signed: Rich: Farnworth.</note>
                  <note>Includes "A letter of James Nayler to severall Friends about Wakefield" (p. 14-16).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Diſcovery of Faith; Wherein is laid down <hi>The Ground of True Faith,</hi> Which Sanctifieth and Purifieth the heart, and worketh out the Carnal part.</p>
            <p>SHEWING <hi>The Way that leadeth to Salvation:</hi> WITH The Difference betwixt the two Seeds, the one of <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> which tendeth to Bondage; and the other, which is the immortal Seed of God, begotten by the immortal word, which liveth and abideth for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being as Iſaac was, the childe of the Promiſe, and of Jeruſalem which is from above, which is the mother of us all that are of the immortal Birth, begotten not by the will of man, but by the will of God; and born again of Water and the Spirit, baptized into one body, and made to drink into one Spirit, having Fellowſhip with the Father and the Son, all ſpringing from one root, and growing into one Body, a habitation for God through the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The difference betwixt The Living WORD and the LETTER.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 John 4. 6.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>We are of God; he that knoweth God, heareth us; he that is not of God, heareth not us; hereby know we the Spirit of truth, and the Spirit of Error.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black Spread Eagle at the weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:166595:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166595:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Friend.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His enſuing Treatiſe was not written for ſwine to ſnuffle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo caſt dirt upon it with their dirty noſes, but from the flowings of love to tender deſires, that they may minde what begets the deſire to Righteouſneſs, and ſo comeout of all mens Words and Writings that doth ariſe out of the corrupt nature; for they are filthy and unclean, the heart of man being deceitful, and that above meaſure, and all words and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings that ariſe out of the firſt nature are corrupt and earthly, and there is no life in them, but for the dead minde that is carnal, which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the things of God, therefore do they not know thoſe that are begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to a lively faith in God, which purifieth their hearts, and worketh out the carnal part, that did delight in the unclean converſation of the world, in conforming to the cuſtoms and faſhions of the world, in Capping and Cringing, Bending and Bowing to men of corrupt hearts, and unpure mindes, all being earthly and brutiſh, following the imaginations of their hearts; idolizing the creatures, falling down to worſhip men more then God, fearing to diſpleaſe men of Corrupt hearts, and unclean converſation, for ſome ſelf end or other, not regarding the command of Jeſus Chriſt, who ſaith Faſhion not your ſelves like unto the world, for the faſhion of the world paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away, &amp; again ſaith he, be not conformed like unto the world, but be ye transformed, by the renewing of your minds; neither be ye men pleaſers, for he that is a man pleaſer, he is no longer the ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, who did not ſeek to pleaſe men, but did the wil of his father, in reproving ſin &amp; evil, and teſtifying againſt the deceits of the world, and that was the reaſon why he was hated of the world, not for any evil, but becauſe ſaith he, I teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the world, that the deeds thereof are evil therefore do the world hate me; and the fair ſayers then came to him and tempting him, ſaying, Maſter we know that thou teacheſt the way of God truly, and that thou careſt for no mans perſon; and the ſubtil ſerpent in the Phariſees lay at catch, and laid ſnares for the innocent, to betray him into the hand of ſinners, that they might have to accuſe him to put him to death, and the Phariſees with the chief Prieſts, they ſought out falſe witneſs to put him to death, becauſe he did teſtifie againſt their deceitfulneſs, hypocriſies and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations; and the bleſſed Spirit in him ſeeing the envy, ſubtilty and venom that lodged in their hearts, and covered over with fine words, and fair pretences, being wiſe to do evil; he ſaid to all that are of the ſeed of Abraham after the Spirit, born again of the ſame Spirit, beware of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166595:3"/> the leaven of the Phariſees, which is hypocriſie; for, ſaith he, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the world are wiſer in their generation, then the children of the light; therefore be ye wiſe as ſerpents, and harmleſs as doves; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the leaven of the Phariſees: now they are alive, the ſame ſeed of evil doers to perſecute, and lies in wait to deſtroy the ſimple ones, who are guided by the pure Wiſdom of God, and are Redeemed from their vain converſation, and walks in obedience to the Commands of Ieſus Chriſt, being guided by the ſame Spirit: God ſending the Spirit of his Son into their hearts, crying Abba Father; and ſaith the bleſſed Spirit of truth, Have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, Epheſ. 5. 11. but he that departs from iniquity, makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a prey; and becauſe that there is not a Running with them into the ſame exceſs of Riot, therefore ſpeak they evil of them, as of evil doers, calling them <hi>Quakers,</hi> or what they can invent, to make them odious in the eyes of the world; but tis nothing but the ſeed of the ſerpent that doth ſo, and it is known by the Spirit of the living God, where Ieſus Chriſt is made manifeſt in Spirit, having deſtroyed the works of the devil, the Spirit of truth and righteouſneſs living in them, it lets them ſee, how the ſeed of the ſerpent lies upon the earth, and grows in the earthly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights; and is covered over with an earthly Profeſſion, and brings forth nothing but weeds and tares, which is for the fire, and muſt be burnt up by the Lord God Almighty, who is the heart ſearcher and tryer. Now friend, if thou do but with a ſingle eye, read this little enſuing Treatiſe, thou wilt not finde any gilded expreſſions in it, that doth ariſe from the wiſdom of the fleſh, for they do but feed the fleſhly minde, which muſt be deſtroyed with a ſore deſtruction; let me intreat thee, that when thou readeſt, thou may firſt return into thy own ſpirit, and ſee how thou standeſt in the fear of the Lord, which is to lay aſide all evil; and ſee that thy underſtanding be kept open as thou readeſt, and thy minde free from all hard thoughts, and opinions of men, which ariſeth out of the dark na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſtand free out of all mens words, that doth ariſe out of the corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and give thy deligence &amp; attention to what thou readeſt as well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as without, and it will ſhew thee the way that leadeth to ſalvatien, and the true guide which it is written from, that thou mayeſt have union with him in the life and ſubſtance of it without all queſtion or doubt, to live in the life and power of the truth it ſelf; for as the lightning cometh out of the eaſt, and ſhineth into the weſt, ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of man be; wait wholly within, and ſink down into the eternal love, and thou wilt ſee me and the reſt, that we are in the unity of that one Spirit, where love is head, the daily bread, where the ſouls refreſhment is for to be had, which makes the heart exceeding glad. Thine in the Vine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rich: Farnworh.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="religious_treatise">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:166595:3"/>
            <head>A Diſcovery of FAITH: WHEREIN Is laid down the ground of true Faith, which ſanctifieth and purifieth the heart, and worketh out the carnal part.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aith purifieth the heart; <note place="margin">1 John 3. 3. Gal. 3. 7. Gen. 12. 21. 1 John 3. 3. Gal. 3. 27, 28. Mat. 15. 19. Ephe. 4. 20. Iam. 3. 14, 15.</note> All who are of faith, are of <hi>Abraham,</hi> they are of one ſeed, come out of their native Countrey, Kingdom and Fathers houſe; they are of one Faith, all of one Faith, if ten thouſand, all Faith in God, which purifies the heart, is one Seed if ten thouſand: the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not the Faith, nor the Letter is not the Seed: many profeſs the Letter, but are not all of one Faith, and this is becauſe they have not the true Faith, which purifies the heart; but it is a formed Faith, ſo your hearts are full of deceits, paſſion, envy, crookedneſs, corrupt, vain Converſation and ſtrife; and thou that art there haſt not learned Chriſt: To profeſs all the Scriptures, and have them in thy notion, wit and memory, yet have not Faith, but the wiſdom of the world, which is carnal, ſenſual and earthly, and the earthly minde, applying the earthly letter to the earthly minde, and the devilliſh nature lodgeth within, killing and devouring the juſt, where it is riſen with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and men and women are bruitiſh, and heatheniſh, and heathens know not God, and all you that know not God at this preſent are heathens: So examine whether you have Faith or no; <note place="margin">1 Iohn 5. 4. Eccleſ. 3. 11. 1 Cor. 1. 21.</note> Faith gives the victory over the world, and then he comes to the end of the world: now you muſt ſee the world to be ſet in your hearts, and the world by their wiſdom, which is earthly and carnal, knows not God; for God is pure, and cannot behold iniquity: Now thou that <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 30. Exod. 33. 11. Gal. 3. 7.</note> ſaith thou haſt wiſdom, ſee if thou know God, or have ſeen him face to face: <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaw him face to face, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw him face to face; and thou that ſayeſt thou haſt Faith, art thou of <hi>Abraham?</hi> for they that have Faith, are of <hi>Abraham;</hi> ſee if thou canſt witneſs the Scripture: for thee to apply the Prophets inheritance, the Apoſtles inheritance, or <hi>Abrahams</hi> inheritance to thy ſelf, and to thy condition, thou thief, the Lord is againſt thee that ſteals the word from thy neighbour; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, <note place="margin">Ier. 23 30, 31.</note> ſaith the Lord, I am againſt them that ſaith, He ſaith, and uſeth their tongues, and I have never ſpoke to them, ſaith the Lord. And do not all the worlds Teachers, and people, all apply the Scriptures,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166595:4"/> and ſay he ſaith, and calls the Letter the Word, <note place="margin">Iohn 1. 1.</note> and ſo live in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, and deceive your ſelves and others: When as the Letter ſaith, God is the Word; and the Letter ſaith, <hi>The Word is ſharper then a two edged ſword, and it divideth aſunder;</hi> but it doth not ſay, that the <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 12.</note> Letter is ſharper then a two edged ſword, and you are clean through the Word, but not through the Letter; and the Letter ſaith, <hi>The Word is a hammer,</hi> but it doth not ſay the Letter is a hammer; and <note place="margin">Iohn 15. 3.</note> the Letter ſaith, <hi>The Wood is a fire,</hi> but doth not ſay, the Letter is as a fire: O hear you outſide faiths, and you outſide mindes, whoſe <note place="margin">Ier. 23. 29.</note> faith is without God, formed and imagined in thy minde; you have the nature of the Devil, to murther; and the nature of the heathen, to rage; the nature of the man-ſlayer, to envy; and you take the Letter for a cloak, and ſay you believe in Chriſt, in the Lord Jeſus. O Hypocrite and Diſſembler, awake, awake! O you blinde guides, <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 1.</note> which have lain long covered, but now the Lord is uncovering you, <note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 18. 19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</note> now he will ſtrip you of your mantles, of your vails, of your broidered atire; now your bracelets, and your bonets, and of your noſe-gaiſes; and now thou ſcarlet coloured harlot that is covered, mincing with thy eyes, and tinckling with thy feet, and thy broider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 16.</note> hair, now thou haſt time to repent, repent, turn to the Lord; but thy own ways thou haſt choſen, and the vain imaginations of thy own heart thou followeſt; ſo thy own deluſions and fear, the Lord will bring upon thee: and all you that ſay you have faith, you ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a great company together, and you profeſs Chriſt, and you have been a long time taught, ſome thirty years, ſome forty, ſome fifty, ſome ſixty, ſome fourſcore, but how many of you have one Faith, and one Seed and Witneſs: examine your ſelves, and deceive not your own ſouls; and you that do profeſs you have faith, you ſay the Letter is the light, and the Scripture Letter is the Word, and the Steple-houſe is the Church, and the ſprinkling of Infants is the baptiſm which you baptize them into, and you have a Teacher, and he teaches you theſe things, and he is called of Men Maſter, which Chriſt cryed wo againſt, and hath the chiefeſt place in the Aſſemblies; but all this while, ſee how many of you are of one faith, and how many of you would lay down your life one for another, and to let your yea, be <note place="margin">Mat 23. 27, 26</note> yea, and your nay, nay in all things; that which purifies the heart, comes from one, and draws to one, if they be ten thouſand, they are one.</p>
            <p>But theſe are them who are purified: now you ſhall ſee a difference between your ſaith, as you call it, and the Saints faith; for the Saints ſaid, their light was Chriſt, and it was within them, and the Saints <note place="margin">1 Iohn 2. 20. 27 1 Theſſ. 1. 1. 1 Cor. 12. 13. Iohn 1 9 Iohn 1. 1. Mat. 23. 6, 7, 8. Gal. 6 7. 2 Theſſ. 1. 8.</note> Light, and the Saints Word was God, and their Teacher was the Anointing, and their Church was in God, and that was their Baptiſm with one Spirit, into one body, and Jeſus Chriſt the ſubſtance of the Prophets, the end of them and of <hi>Moſes:</hi> them that were called of men Maſters, and was got up into the chiefeſt place in the Aſſemblies, he cryed againſt ſuch, and ſuch you hold up: And are not all your
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166595:4"/> Teachers called of men Maſters? do you think God will be mocked with your words? though you may take him for your cloak a while, <note place="margin">Mat. 2. 1, 2, 3, 4</note> he will come with flames of fire, and will recompence upon all you: he that follows him obeys him, and he that doth obey him, doth not hold up that which he cryed out againſt: <hi>Herods</hi> hard heart exalted, he gathered all the chief Prieſts, to know of them where Chriſt ſhould be born and they ſaid, in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Judea,</hi> it is written, ſo ſaith the Prophet; here they could tell by the Letter where he ſhould be born, and when he was come, they had no faith in him: and all you now that tell by the Letter, where Jeſus Chriſt was born, where he was crucified, at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to ſay he hath dyed for all; yet here is no faith in Chriſt, though you may know all this by the Letter except that you can witneſs the life that you live is by the faith of <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 20.</note> Chriſt, and there the Apoſtle ſpeaks his life, and you take his words: now every one in particular, who comes to witneſs Jeſus Chriſt, muſt witneſs him born in them; and Chriſt is not the Letter, for the Letter is death, it is a declaration of Chriſt, and all who have Chriſt made manifeſt, the works of the Devil deſtroyed, and if thou <note place="margin">Iohn 5. 29. 40. 1 Iohn 3. 8.</note> canſt not witneſs the works of the Devil deſtroyed, Jeſus Chriſt is not yet made manifeſt, therefore what thou doſt profeſs, a thing without thee, and thy heart is full of deceit, and no faith at all, no not ſo much as a grain of muſtard ſeed, and a grain of muſtard ſeed is but a little thing to the outward eye; but thou art proud <hi>Lucifer,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt 17. 20. Gal. 3. 7. 2 Cor. 3 2.</note> who art mounted up with thy knowledge, when thou art thrown down, thou ſhalt ſee that thou haſt no faith: For all who are of Faith, are of <hi>Abraham,</hi> they are one Seed, one Heart, yea, written in one anothers hearts; therefore all you who follow this cuſtomary teaching of the world, ſee how many of you are of one heart and one ſoul: now you ſhall ſee your ſelves without this faith, perverſe one to another, fighting and brawling, and devouring one another, ſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and living in wantonneſs, fulneſs, gluttony, and abundance of idleneſs, devouring the juſt, and the Creation: ſee that theſe be the ſins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> juſt <hi>Lot</hi> vexed his righteous ſoul, with all their ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 7.</note> deeds: now where ſouls are raiſed up by the ſame power, are grieved with you, the ſame generation and nature as was in them, and you envying one another, quarrelling with one another for the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yea for old hedges, old houſes, going to Law one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and here you ſhew Prieſts and people, that your affections are <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 5. Pail. 3. 20. Col. 3 1.</note> in the earth: now your Teachers who are examples, go to Law, ſo do the people go to Law one with another, which ſhews that there is not a wiſe man amongſt you: and ſo your converſation is in the earth, our converſation is in heaven: and thy affections that are in the earth, thou haſt nothing to do to profeſs the Saints conditions, for thy minde is earthly, luſting after earthly things, which paſſeth away, and ſo evil conceivings lodges in thy minde: therefore all men <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 20.</note> and women, profeſs no more then you do poſſeſs: For no man in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> that holds up that which Chriſt ſpeaks againſt, hath ſaith in Chriſt,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166595:5"/> neither People nor Prieſt, for who had faith in Jeſus, denyed the Prieſts, which were true types of him, and who hath faith now denies all the blind Prieſts, who are types of nothing, but are Antichriſts, and them hath God never ſent.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ALL people weigh and try your ſelves, where you are, whether you be in the ſtate of <hi>Iſhmael. Iſhmael</hi> was the firſt birth, and he was a ſcoffer, an Archer, his hand was againſt every man, and all you, who are in the firſt birth, are <hi>Iſhmaels,</hi> ſcoffers, mockers, and wilde as <note place="margin">Gen. 21. 9. Gal 4. 29. Gen. 16. 11, 12</note> 
                  <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was, who was a wild man, whoſe hand was againſt every man. <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not ſo, the ſecond birth, he was the ſeed, in him was none of the firſt nature; ſo all who are of the ſame Seed witneſſeth him, and <note place="margin">Gen. 21. 12.</note> witneſſes the other; and <hi>Eſau</hi> was the firſt birth, and he was a profane perſon, a cunning hunter, having the fat of the earth, bearing the ſword, <note place="margin">Gen. 25. 25. Gen. 25 27. Gen. 27. 40. Iſa. 49. 17. John 3. 3.</note> who was a place for Dragons, a wilderneſs, and deſolate, whoſe por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was <hi>Mount Scir:</hi> and all you who are in the firſt birth, are as hee was, are ye not ſeeking after the fat of the earth, bearing the Sword, and a Wilderneſs, devouring one another, cunning hunters, hunting up and down, whoſe portion is in <hi>Mount Seir,</hi> all ſtriving for it; but <hi>Jacob</hi> his portion was not ſuch, he was a plain man and perfect, dwelling in <note place="margin">Gen. 25. 27.</note> Tent, God ſaw no iniquity in him. O Man and Woman, art thou here, art thou plain? art thou perfect? doſt thou dwell in Te<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts? A ſtanding place, doth God ſee no iniquity in thee? this was <hi>Jacob</hi> the ſecond birth. <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now all people, ſlatter not your ſelvs, read your ſelves whether you be in the firſt or ſecond birth; there is a light within you, wil tell you hearkning unto it, which will condemn you to God if you lye: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be juſt and fear the Lord, for dreadfull is he, and terrible to the Wicked; for the fear of the Lord keeps the heart clean; and <hi>Cain</hi> was <note place="margin">Iohn 1. 5. Iohn 1 9. Mal. 4. 1. Gen. 4. 5. Gen 4. 8. Iſa. 1. 11.</note> the firſt, and <hi>Eve</hi> was deceived in her firſt birth, and <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice God did not accept, he was in envie, a murderer: And all you who are in the firſt birth, you are in envie, and God doth not accept your Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Read your ſelves, and honeſtly conſider, while you have envie in you, you are <hi>Cains,</hi> while you are in the firſt birth you are <hi>Cains,</hi> and your ſacrifice God doth not accept. <hi>Abel,</hi> the ſecond, was not ſo, he was not a man-ſlayer, he did not envie, he was a righteous man, and his Sacrifice God did accept: ſo all who are come into the ſecond <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 4. Mal. 4. 3, 4. 1 Iohn 5. 6.</note> birth, to offer up a ſacrifice according to the Scripture, in righteouſnes to God, God doth accept them as its his own. All holy praiſes bee unto thee, O God for ever, who art righteous, and delightſt in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes; who are holy, and delightſt in holineſs; who are pure, and canſt not behold iniquity; for the workers of iniquity muſt depart into curſing. Thou maiſt ſay thou are redeemed by the precious bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, but they that are redeemed, are redeemed from their vain <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 41.</note> converſation; now canſt thou witneſs this, that thou are redeemed from thy vain converſation, by the precious bloud of Jeſus Chriſt: All <note place="margin">1 Pkt. 1. 18, 19.</note>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:166595:5"/> who read theſe things, read your ſelves, and ſee if you can witneſs theſe things, read them not without you, but within; Things have bin long put afar off, the Apoſtle told of an <hi>Eſau</hi> amongſt them then, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <note place="margin">Rom. 9 13. Amos 1. 11. Mal. 1. 2. Gen. 3. 15. 1 John 2. 11. 1 Joh. 1. 7. Mat. 2. 16. Gal. 5. 19, 20, 22.</note> told of an <hi>Eſau</hi> then, and the Apoſtle told of a <hi>Cain</hi> amongſt the Saints, and the ſame nature that was is, the firſt birth, the ſecond birth is, they that come to witneſs it, know it; there's but two Seeds, two Wayes, read your ſelves, light and darkneſs: ſee whether you are in; he that walks in darkneſs the fruit of darkneſs ſhews it; he that walks in the light, the fruits of the light make it manifeſt, Let your light ſo ſhine before men, as that you may glorifie your heavenly Father, which is in heaven; He that walks in the fleſh, the fruits of the fleſh makes it manifeſt, and ſhews it forth; and he that walks in the Spirit, the fruits of the Spirit ſhews it forth: ſo deceive not your ſelves, God will not be mocked with words, and doe not take him for a cleak, making a profeſſion, and live in deceit; for woe unto him that is covered, and not with the Spirit of the Lord: therefore ſtay your ſelves and ſee, and <note place="margin">Gal 6. 7. Iſa. 3 1.</note> be not haſty, nor raſh, nor fierce, but honeſtly ſtay your ſelves on the Lord, and ſee your ſelves the Prodigall, when he ſaw himſelf what hee had done, went home unto his Fathers houſe; and thou haſt read of a Prodigall in the Scripture that fed among Swine, but doſt thou ſee thy ſelf to be the Prodigall feeding among the Swine, feeding on <note place="margin">Luke 15. 20, 16</note> Husks: Is this opened unto thee? doſt thou know what this Husk is, thou muſt not read this Parable without knowing it, but within thee; when thou ſeeſt thy ſelf, thou wilt witneſs this thing with me, when thou are come to thy Fathers houſe, thou wilt rejoice with me, and ſee that thou haſt bin ſeeding among the Swine, the Letter, the outſide which profits not.</p>
               <p>To all that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and turns away from Fables, light Speeches, filthy talking, curſed Speaking, idle Jeſting, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in cleanneſſe of life, who have Families, Children, and Servants, I charge you by the Lord be paterns and examples to them, and all in Wiſdom and gravity, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, teaching Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren humbleneſſe, meekneſſe and tenderneſſe, which leads to the fear of the Lord, and let no corrupt communication come out of your mouth, left children and Servants learn it, and there thou are a patern of evil: Nor no filthy jeſting, nor light Talk<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leſt thou be an example of evil, for one teaches and learns of another; and while the evil cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deceipt lodgeth, its hatehing and inventing evill, and ſo others learns of it, and ſo who are wicked, learns wickedneſs, and grows up in it. Therefore all you who are lovers of Jeſus Chriſt. ſhun the occaſion of ſuch, and have no fellowſhip with ſuch, for they be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull workers, but rather reprove them: And you which be Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants fear the Lord, and be diligent, ſerving the Lord, who have Dames, Maſters and Miſtreſſes, as they call them, which live in rioting, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe and pride, exceſſe and lying, oaths, fooliſh ſongs and jeſting, ſhun the occaſion of ſuch, for they are evill examples, and practiſe not ſuch things, but wait upon the Lord; and whatſoever ye doe, doe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166595:6"/> it as unto the Lord, but to you that have Families, that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and all his Saints, reall in power, love and mercy wilbe multiplyed among you, and you that be Servants, labor in love as unto the Lord, and children walk in love and ſoberneſs, ſo God is, the head who is love, amongſt you all to be a family of Love; and all the creation is the Lords; and all that you doe, doe it as unto the Lord, not with compulſion, rigor and hardneſs, for that's the ſloathful Servant that lives in the earth without the fear of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou that haſt applyed all the Promiſes, Redemption and Salvation, thou ſha't ſee to thy ſelf is due nothing but curſes, woe, miſery, and condemnation, and deſtruction for that nature, and ſelf is out of the truth, and is not reconciled to any thing; he that is reconciled to God, is reconciled to all things, he is come out of death, which hath paſt over all, he is not of this world, he ſees all the world paſſeth away, he is eſcaped from the pollutions, he hath put off the body of ſin, with the filth of the fleſh, it is he by whom all things were made in the beginning, and who were with him when all things were made: Who are of the world, knows him not, but is a preſerver, and it is he that rejoyceth in the heavens, which the world cannot contain; it is he, whoſe words are the words of life; he is a ſaviour, but they are deſtroyers: Thou that canſt contain this, haſt laid hold upon eternall life; thou that heareſt his voice haſt life; he that hears the voice of the Son of God ſhall live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The death which hath paſt over all men, is but one, and Chriſt Jeſus took upon him not the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of Abraham. which the death haſt paſt over; now thou that haſt not the ſame Spirit that raiſed up: Jeſus Chriſt from the death, is none of his, and all the promiſes is to the ſeed, which ſeed is but one, which is Chriſt in you; who are of Faith are of Abraham, cald out of the heatheniſh nature and worſhips, and out of their native Countrey, as Abraham was, and are of Abraham, and thouſands do witneſſe it, one Faith, one ſeed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The difference betwixt the Word of God and Letter.</head>
               <p>IN the beginning was the Word, and none knows this Word, but who are come into the beginning; now all people and Prieſts who can witneſs this? who are come hither? into the beginning, what our hands have handled, what our eyes have ſeen, what was from the beginning, the Word of life, this declare we unto you, who knovvs this Word is pure, and are made clean through the Word, are waſhed by it, are ſanctified by it, are cut in pieces by it, &amp; are divided aſunder by it: This Word is a Hammer beating down every thing, that the ſeed of God may riſe up, and all who know this Word may come to the beginning, it is as a fire burning up all corruptions, and this is the Word that is nigh thee, in thy heart; And this is the Word which all the Prophets ſpoke from; and this is the Word that became Fleſh, and dwelt amongſt us ſaith the Saints; and this is the Word of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166595:6"/> life which the Apoſtles preached, the ſubſtance of all figures, types and ſhadows; and this is the Word which makes all the Saints one, that reconciles their hearts together to the Lord; this is the Word by which all things ſtands and remains, and are upheld, by his Word and power; and this is the Word which doth endure for ever, all vvho are born again of the immortall ſeed witneſs this Word with me: And now the Word is made manifeſt, the ſame as ever was, vvhich gathers together the hearts of all people, which divides aſunder the precious and vile, and of twain hath made one; and this is the VVord that lets ſee, that fleſh is graſs; and this is the VVord which was before any Letter was written, and all who have not this VVord, puts the Letter for the Word, and are in <hi>Cains</hi> nature, envying and murdering, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on ſwiftly; and <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice God doth not accept, and all the Preaching, and all the Praying, and all your Reading, and all your Singing, and all your Expounding, and all your Churches, and all your Worſhips, and all your Teachers, and all your Baptiſmes, which are invented from the Letter, the carnall minde invents them; all this is for the fire, your profeſſion muſt be gathered together in bundles, and caſt into the fire, for they are the works of the fleſh, proceeding from the firſt nature, &amp; not knowing the Word of God, but only the Letter, ye crucifie the juſt, and ye get up in the juſts place, quenching the light within you, the deceipt transforms in his place, as <hi>Cain</hi> did when he ſlew his brothen <hi>Abell,</hi> he gets up into his brothers place, and ſaid, <hi>Am I my Brothers keeper?</hi> ſo all you who crucify the juſt, ye are as <hi>Cain,</hi> for it is the righteous that God doth accept, the ſecond birth; As you read <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice God did not accept, but <hi>Abel</hi> the ſecond God did accept, for he was righteous. And <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe <hi>Abels</hi> works were righteous and <hi>Cains</hi> were evil: now all you who are in the firſt birth are <hi>Cain,</hi> in envy, manſlayers, and your ſacrifice God doth not accept: ſee whether you be in envy or no, now all that come to the Word, come before <hi>Cain</hi> was; All the Prophets of the Lord ſpoke from this Word, and then the falſe Prophets got the true Prophets form of words, but had not the Word: then the Lord ſent his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which had his Word, to cry againſt the Prophets that ſpoke a Divination of their own brain, and ſteal my Word from their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, and uſe their tongue, and ſay, the Lord ſaith, when the Lord hath not ſpoken unto them: and as it was then, ſo it is now, all the Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the World ſpeak a Divination of their own brain, and not from the mouth of the Lord, the Lord is againſt them now, I witneſſe it by the ſame Word as ever was, and ſo they draw people unto the Letter, and tels them it is the Word, and to hearken to them, who ſpeak their vain imaginations of it, ſo they bear rule by their meanes over the poor people, which the Lord was ever againſt, for God is free and he wil have his people ſo; and his Goſpell is a free Goſpell, and his mercies are free, and his Grace is free; his Goſpell is free to every Creature, and his Grace is free to every Creature; his Grace is not the letter, the Goſpel is not the letter, his glad tydings is not the letter,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166595:7"/> for many poor troubled Souls may lie in death and condemnation, and have the Letter: And theſe Teachers of the Letter, and there lay wounded, but no peace till Jeſus Chriſt come, the glad tydings, the free Goſpell, then will you witneſs with me, That the Goſpell is a free Goſpel, and not to be bought and ſold for mony, and the grace of God is free; <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth, come to the water of life; he that hath no money, come buy wine and milk without money and without price;</hi> And hearken diligently that your ſouls may live, <hi>And I will make an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of David.</hi> So all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple conſider, and ſee if you can witneſs your Souls are raiſed out of death, and you brought into this everlaſting Covenant; for who can witneſs their Souls brought out of death, are come into the beginning; but thou that haſt nothing but the Letter, and are ſpending thy money and thy labor, and not ſatisfied, ſpending thy money for that which is not bread, thou art following the greedy dumb Doggs, which never have enough: <hi>Baals</hi> prieſts, which have forſaken the right way, going after the error of <hi>Baalam,</hi> running after the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs, who ever ſlew the juſt in the particular, deſpiſeth the birthright, <hi>Cain</hi> like ſlaying the righteous, and who ſayes it in the particular, the ſame nature ſlayes it in the generall, where the righteous Seed guides and rules, and is the head; ſo the generation of <hi>Cain</hi> is but one, which is the firſt birth: Now loving the light, it will guide you to God from all men, that you need never look at man more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the Miniſters of Chriſt, many of them, were Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and no Maſters.</head>
               <p>TO all who are ignorant and blind people, who a long time have been deceived by blind guides, who have told you that Learned men and Scholars muſt open the Scriptures, which is a thing contrary to the Scripture, and croſſeth the Scriptures to ſay ſo; for there was not many of them learned in the Letter, and ſpoke forth the life of the Scriptures which made learned men to wonder. <hi>Paul</hi> was a learned man, but while he was in that condition, he was an enemy to Chriſt, and that hinderd, but he was a ſtrict Phariſee and a Perſecuter; and when he knew Jeſus Chriſt he denyed all his learning, and then hee ſpoke forth the Scriptures. He was a Tentmaker; <hi>Amos</hi> a Herdſman, a keeper of carrell; and the Apoſtles many of them Fiſhermen: Theſe gave forth the Scriptures; theſe were the Miniſters of God, made by God not by man: <hi>David, Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were keepers of ſheep, and ſuch as theſe ſpoke forth the Scriptures. They were plain men, keepers of cattel; <hi>Eliſha</hi> was a ploughman; theſe were plain men, and thoſe were an abomination to the <hi>Egiptians;</hi> would it not be an abominable thing, and abomination to you who are <hi>Egiptians,</hi> and in the <hi>Egiptian-</hi>wiſdom
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166595:7"/> to ſee a ſhepherd or a Tent-maker come and preach, or a Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to come and preach, which was not learned; or a Herdſman come among you and preach in the Kings Chappel, as <hi>Amos</hi> did, and they would not let him, and yet yee will make a trade of his words; or to ſee a man come from the Plough, or a Threſher preach; ſuch kinde of men as theſe gave forth the Scriptures, taught of God, not brought up and taught and learned by the will of man, for by that learning no man knows God, but that knowledg lifts up in pride, and makes them Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and lord it over people and creatures; but who are made miniſters by the will of God, and not by the will of man, are Servants to all. Now here is a diſtinction between the Miniſters of the world, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God, the one is Maſters over all, the other is Servants to all; and they who are in their own will ſet up, the Miniſters made by the will of man, and denies them who are made Miniſters by the will of God; and they who are made Miniſters by the will of man, ſay that the Letter which is carnall is the light; and that the Letter is the Word, the Steeple-houſe the Church, the 4. Books <hi>Mathew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Goſpel; Hebrew, Greek and Latin theſe are the tongues; <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> two well heads of Divinity; and the Letter and the Spirit inſoparable; and the Spirit is in the Letter, and that learned men muſt raiſe it out: Now they who are made Miniſters by the will of God, their Word is God, their light is Chriſt, their Church is in <hi>God,</hi> their record is the Spirit, their original is the Word, which was before all tongues, which opens tongues; their Goſpel is Jeſus Chriſt the lamb of God, prepared before the world was, which was before the World was, ſalvation is in God, the Spirit is within them, and they are the ſons of God that are guided by his Spirit: The Spirit is not in the Letter, but it is within, as it was in them that ſpoke forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. So all people weigh and try your Teachers, and let the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures be your rule, which you doe profeſs in words, the life of the Scriptures is the Saints rule and guide within them; the World pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth the Letter to be their rule, yet walk contrary to it; the Saints baptiſme is with one Spirit into one body, the worlds baptiſm is in ſprinkling a little Water, which they ſay they baptiſe into the Church withall; there is not one example among the Saints for them to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe ſuch a thing, yet profeſſing the Letter to be the rule, they act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it: Oh blind Hypocrites! the blind leads the blind, ſo both fall into the ditch: The bread the Saints break is the body of Chriſt, and the Cup they drink is the blood of Chriſt, and are all made to drink into one Spirit; and the Cup the World take is a little Bread and Wine, and they call that a Sacrament, which there is no Scripture for, and ſo ſhew forth the ſpirit of error; who hath an ear to hear, may hear, and who can reach to theſe things, may receive them; the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters made by the will of God, their fountain is God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:166595:8"/>
               <head>A Letter of <hi>James Nayler</hi> to ſeverall Friends about <hi>Wakefield.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>JAmes</hi> a priſoner of Jeſus Chriſt,</signed> 
                  <salute>unto all that love the appearance of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt every where, grace and peace be multiplyed from God the Father, and from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>My dear hearts, you whom the Lord hath manifeſted ſo much love unto, as to call you out of ſin and death, and the world, all the delights and pleaſures of the world, which fades away, up to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, where is joy unſpeakable, pleaſures and riches that endure for evermore, Dear friends, watch and be ſober, that you may hear the voice of your beloved when he calleth, and let not the precious proffers of the love of God be tendred in vain; while you have an ear open to the world, you cannot hear the voice of God, ſo that you have bin made to groan under it: how long have you been deceived by it all your time, promiſing peace, fulneſs, and ſatisfaction, but have bin brought to cry out of oppreſſion and deceit, and your cries are come before the Lord of Sabbaths, who is your reſt, and he is now appeared to deliver you, and ſet you free from bondage, that you may ſerve him alone. And now take heed of conſulting with your old maſter; hath the Lord been ſo mercifull unto you, as that he hath ſet your faces out of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> towards the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed land, O take heed of looking back, left you be taken captive, and led back again, and ſo you come ſhort of redemption, and your faith fail you, and ſo you come ſhort of the promiſe, for unbelief cannot enter into the reſt; but you, Dear friends, put on reſolution, put on ſtrength, be valiant for your freedome, caſt off every weight, follow your Captain the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who for the joy ſet before him, indured the croſs, deſpiſed the ſhame, and ſo entred into reſt and glory. Take heed of halting between God and the World; what agreement can there be or what peace, while you are married to the world? Your thoughts turn in thither, and you are adulterated from God, who gives you all good things, as ſo many tokens of his love; hereby is the broken language brought forth, and you cannot ſpeak the pure language of the land of reſt. And while you give way to that in you, which leads you to look back to what is behind you; you keep your ſelves in the wilderneſs and darkneſs, and loſe your way, and know not where you are, grieving the holy Spirit of the Lord which hath appeared unto you to guide you to but (O friends!) mind your guide, and follow him; Ariſe, ſhine, your light is come, and the glory of the Lord is come upon you, the night is far ſpent, the day is at hand, even the day of Sions deliverance; Ariſe, come away all you that love her, come off from the World and worldly things, come into the life, lie no longer in death and dead things. Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ſtand up from the dead, that Chriſt may give thee light: Come forth, come forth of all created things, witneſs your redemption to all the world, that you are redeemed from the earth upto God, out of all kindreds, tongues, people, and nations, to reign as Kings and Prieſts for ever, above the world, ſin and death. triumphing and treading upon all that would take you captive: This is the day of your deliverance, own it with the loſs of all fading pleaſures, make it appear to all the world, this is the day you waited for, even the day of your joy, but of the worlds ſorrow: A day of blackneſs and gloomineſs, a day of fear and trouble to them that oppreſs you; a day wherein the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt ſhall be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166595:8"/> exalted, and all the kingdoms and powers of the earth ſhaken; a day wherein the Lord will avenge the power of him that is too ſtrong for him: Rejoyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce ye meek of the earth, ſhout for joy ye poor deſpiſed ones, whom your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren have troden upon, and have caſt you out, and you have been made their mocking-ſtocks for the truths ſake, Sing and rejoyce, the voice of a King is amongſt you, and he will marry you to himſelf in righteouſneſs, purity, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and will rejoyce over you, as a bridegroom over the bride, and you ſhall be for a crown of glory in the hand of the Lord; and a royall Diademe in the hand of your God. O my dear hearts, my deſire to God for you all is, that you might come to ſee what unſpeakable riches is laid up for you in Jeſus Chriſt, which is hid from all fleſh, neither can you ſee it while you live in the fleſh; and while you continue your love to the world and worldly things, you keep out the manifeſtation of the Fathers love, for your hearts canot receive both, Now ſhew your ſelves wiſe men, chooſe that which is eternal, here is light and life tendred you in Jeſus Chriſt, freely out of the Fathers love, freely receive life and love, and ſhew forth life and love to God again, by giving up to him all you have and all you are for Chriſts ſake, that ſo you may come to receive all again with Chriſt, who is the fulneſs of the Fathers love, and in him are all good things needfull for this life, and that which is to come, even the earneſt of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance which none can take from you, which once being received, you ſhall never hunger more, having a wel ſpring within even the witneſs of eternal life and love; and as Chriſt appears, who is our life and love, ſo ſhall life and love appear, ſpring, bloſſom, and bring forth fruit towards God and man; that ſo being raiſed with him from death and dead works, you may henceforth live unto God, and being brought into oneneſs with him, and purity, and holineſs, you may be one amongst your ſelves, of one heart and one minde, ſpeaking one and the ſelf ſame thing, and having the ſame care one for another, as for your ſelves. And take heed that there be not in any of you a principle of ſelf-love, which once having, will lead to ſeparation and diviſion, caſting a ſtumbling block in the way of the ſimple; and ſo they that are weak being defiled and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned back into the world. And I beſeech you brethren that you mark them that once ſet their faces towards Sion, but not being willing to deny the world, and take up the Croſs, have conſulted with fleſh and blood, and turned back into <hi>Egypt</hi> again, of ſuch take heed, knowing that the ſame ſpirit that hath wrought in them deceitfully, will not ceaſe to work by them to deceive others to maintain its own Kingdom; but you ſtanding faſt in the pure light of Chriſt, you ſhall ſee whither theſe return, and the cauſe of their returnings, and that the end of ſuch is worſe then the beginning; but there muſt be ſuch, that they who are approved may be made manifeſt. But you my Brethren, be ye ſo far from following ſuch, that their falling away may cauſe you to watch and ſearch by what power you ſtand, and ſo a pure fear may be preſerved in you, by which you may be kept in the way that leads to the Crown which is immortall: for it is he that overcomes that muſt wear the Crown, wherefore faint not, nor think any thing hard, the Lord cals unto you, nothing muſt ſuffer but that which is to die, that your ſouls may live: O your light affliction worketh for you a far more exceeding weight of glory, while you keep your eye to that which is invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; wherefore give up your ſelves to his will in all things, Stand in the will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166595:9"/> of God in your preſent condition, you are my joy in the Lord; let ny benelste refreſhed to hear of your ſtedfaſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſs and growth in the Truth: Take heed of propounding ends to your ſelves in any thing, for that leads out of the way of God, and gives way to your own wiſdom; and ſo you ſeek to preſerve that alive which is appointed for death, and ſo you maintain war againſt God, and knows not; and in this condition you can have no peace, while the enemies are in arms againſt your peace. O, dear Friends, you are in my heart, my prayer to God for you is, that you may be kept blameleſs to the ceming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, bleſſed for ever. My fellow priſoner, and dear companion in the Lord ſalutes you all: Ceaſe not to pray for us, that we may be kept to his praiſe, who hath counted us worthy to ſuffer for his Name, we are well, and in great peace, kept in our Fathers love; above all, we are often brought to ſtand and wonder how we are kept in the midſt of the fire, and yet not conſumed; and the more that the enemy rages, the more are we kept in peace within: Here are ſtrange De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices uſed to inſnare us, to get ought againſt us (true or falſe) but all is Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by a power the World knows not, God is our ſtrength; Rejoyce with us all, dear Friends, and praiſe his Name for evermore, for he is worthy, for his Mercy endures for ever.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>JAMES NAYLER. A Priſoner at <hi>Appleby</hi> in Weſtmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land for the Truths ſake.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
